welcome to asking anything I'm Jack I
had a couple of technical difficulties
with the interview with golf Western
yesterday somehow the first half hour of
the interview was not recorded there
were some audio drops online and the
quality of my video isn't too great I
had some connectivity issues find out it
was running really slow it was lagging I
think I was asking too much of this
machine but I tried to sell if it's what
I could there's still two hours left of
the interview what wasn't recorded was
the introduction cross explanation of
his free energy principle which if you
are interested you can find on YouTube I
especially would recommend his interview
with curry mango on the theories of
everything Channel which I just keep
recommending having said that if you're
feeling particularly generous consider
donating to my patreon at patreon.com
asking anything
while you're watching please like
subscribe so let me just introduce Dr
Carl first in a free energy farceer
neuroscientific Nomad Bayesian brain
blacksmith computational connoisseur
he's an interpretaming Titan shaping our
understanding of the brain and cognition
his work on the free energy principle
offers a unified framework for this
servering the complex dynamics of
biological systems with the career
spending three decades Carl has
navigated the Realms of theoretical
Neuroscience computational modeling and
systems biology influencing our
interpretation of the brains intricate
workings he has authored over 800
scientific papers marking transformative
strides in this field
enjoy
he talks a little bit about a little bit
about Consciousness and
um I am curious how your work relates to
there are two other prominent theories
of Consciousness such as for example
integrated information Theory uh Global
workspace Theory Quantum Consciousness
Theory
um and higher order thought Theory
and I'm not sure I I have a suspicion
you know at least three or four of those
but how does your work relate to those
theories
I get a very interesting question in
fact um with colleagues
um specifically colleagues like Maxwell
ramstead and Adam saffron and um and
others we've just written a series of
papers looking at a minimum minimum
unifying model of Consciousness that
speaks to a lot of a lot of those
theories so I can answer your question
quite expertly because I'm glad I just
read papers so
um
they all have to a greater lesser extent
um something in common with
um and consilient with the free energy
principle and I say that because you um
you have to remember and I am always
reminded of this by yaakov hell the free
energy principle is not a principle that
you can apply to produce a theory of
Consciousness so it's not it's not there
to explain consciousness
um so
um it probably plays a useful role when
applied to various theories of
Consciousness
um and you know when you when you do
apply it then you know I generally you
find I repeat a lot of concealings so
let's just take the global workspace
Theory
um so
if you look at the mechanics of active
inference that would be an application
the free energy principle to a brain for
example
um and look at the various process there
is such as predictive coding and
predictive processing then you can see
um direct homologues or aspects of
global global neuronal workspace and
workspace Theory and indeed Global
workspace Theory emerge from first
principles so what are those first
principles well we've just said that the
the game that we can understand
processing in the brain as a process of
inference under some kind of world model
or gerited model that entails the space
of hypotheses that we bring to the table
to expand our Sensations what kind of
model is it well we know two things
about it in the spirit of the good
regulator theorem or the notion that in
order to successfully explain
are sensory input are models of that the
world generating those uh inputs are
World models have to have a degree of
ethomorphism with the way that the
sensations are generated which just
means that the internal World models or
generative models entailed by our brain
have to have both a dynamic because of
the importance of time we're talking
about processes here and hierarchical
structure and as soon as you say that
and then you work out the uh Bayesian
mechanics or the free energy minimizing
dynamics that play out on these Dynamic
hierarchical generative models you get
to something that looks very very much
like a global neuronal workspace first
of all there is something deep in this
centripetal hierarchy that is informed
by and predicts and tries to explain
lower levels that are towards the
surface of the centripetal hierarchy
furthermore not everything gets to the
the set the uh the um the global
workspace in the sense I have to be able
to attend to certain sensory inputs in
order to grease the pathways to give
those kinds of prediction errors for
example privileged access to deeper
levels of processing so this is what
this is if you're a psychologist you you
would recognize as attention if you were
an engineer you'd recognize it as trying
to optimize the Kalman gain
mathematically it's just a question of
selecting those newsworthy prediction
errors that convey precise information
and estimating the Precision and thereby
enabling those prediction errors to
ignite and induce basic belief updating
deep in the hierarchy so that would be
if you're like a mathematicians or a
um a computational neuroscientist
description of global neural workspace
so just knowing that you have to have a
dynamic hierarchical model would suggest
that the constructs that one that
emerges under uh Global neuronal
workspace there is uh you know um are
almost
must almost be true
and are emergent from applying the free
energy principle to those characteristic
charitable models that you'd see in
things like you and me
um the um integrated information Theory
that's slightly
um slightly more distant
um in terms of
it's relative to the free energy
principle because
um integrated information theory is
really a description it's an axiomatic
um
theory that they is based upon a handful
of axioms that must be true or are
assumed to be true and true of
Consciousness and then it tries to
um identify certain uh information
theoretic characteristics of systems
that that possess these axiomatic
characteristics so it's not really
um a simple principle in the sense of
the free energy principle it's more a
consequence of committing to certain
axioms however those commitments
um lead to something that looks very
very similar to the free energy
principle in terms of
um a set of partitions
um that are trying to in some way
maximize Mutual information but between
those partitions
in a distributed set of states that are
all influencing each other and again
that sparsity of connectivity is exactly
what underwrites the hierarchical
structures that we're talking about
previously so if you think about it how
do I make see a graph or a network
hierarchical I just remove any
connections that jump over too many
levels I just render it very very sparse
so that it has a set of partitions
technically these are Markov blankets
that Define the thinners you know if a
hierarchical level in my brain is a
thing then it has to have a Markov
blanket if it has a markup blanket that
induces a certain kind of partitioning
and sparsity of influencer and
connections furthermore
the emphasis of a special kind of
distributed Mutual information that is
inherent and in IIT is can be read as an
important aspect or part of variational
free energy so in order to
predict well
in order to maximize the evidence for my
generative models of a sensed world
I effectively have to maximize Mutual
information
between my explanations for what's going
on out there and what is actually going
on out there that actually entails a
maximization of the neutral information
between my internal representations with
the my generative model of my world
model and the sensory fluctuations
providing the evidence that's helping me
revise my beliefs about what's going on
those fluctuations in particular coding
would be the prediction errors but all
that also holds true in a hierarchical
setting so not only am I trying to
maximize much information between what's
going on in my head and what's going on
in my world in fact in this instance in
your head so that we can engage in this
kind of generalized synchronizationally
shared narrative and conversation and
I'm doing that generally with my entire
lived world but I'm also trying to
maximize Mutual information with my
sensorium but also all the inner screens
that constitute the different levels of
my generative model
so now we're right back to where IIT
would uh would would want you to be
you're trying to maximize much
information in a particular way over
partitions that I would read in terms of
a heterogical carving nature at its
joints inside your genitive model in
terms of higher order thought Theory
um that almost emerges for free as soon
as you talk about hierarchical gelatin
models you can't have a you can't have
any inference that is not if you like
apt for descriptions under higher order
thought theories
um as soon as you commit to hierarchical
predictive coding and hierarchogenic
models so the whole point of having
nested
um
hierarchical levels that our generative
model where each level is trying to
predict the level below right down to
the sensorium
um is that you are effectively have
inducing higher and higher order
inference processes so that you know
there may be some very deep one or more
distributed systems that are trying to
predict their Markov blanket which is
another system inside the brain very
much like an onion and so on all the way
out to the sensory cortices and
ultimately our sensory epithelia so at
some point you are going to encounter
um especially in those kinds of
creatures or gelatin models or creatures
that entail models that are have this
aspect of agency and the capacity to
plan into the future
and you're furthermore internalize
action so internal action mental action
is just basically selecting the data on
the inside
um and that will correspond to attention
you've now got this deep link now
between attention and conscious
processing under higher order thought
theory that emerges simply because I
have to have a model of the consequences
of my sense making even if it's within
my skull and within my hierarchical
model and
through that you now start to tell a
story about well what am I modeling I'm
modeling myself modeling my data so
you'll have a natural it is
quintessentially higher order just in
Virtual it being uh just in virtue of
having a hierarchical
world or gerited model which you need in
order to uh to uh to minimize to do your
self-efficiency or to minimize your free
energy
was there a fourth one I can't remember
um let me see information integrated
mystery Global work phase Theory Quantum
conscience Theory and higher order
thought Theory those were the four most
popular ones
yes uh well very briefly um yeah I would
read the quantum formulations very much
along the lines that is emerging at the
moment
um described by people like Chris field
and Jim playsbrook and Mike Levin
um so they've um they recently come up
with this notion of an inner screen
hypothesis which a lot of my colleagues
are quite excited about And subscribe to
which is exactly uh well first of all
let me just qualify why this is a
Quantum uh approach it is not that the
Consciousness emerges at the level of uh
very small quantum physics it's the fact
that you could understand anything from
the point of view of quantum information
Theory and
um
a particular aspect that Chris and
colleagues focus on is the notion of a
holographic screen that allows two
systems to couple to each other so the
bulk of one system reading and writing
of the holographic screen under
holographic principle
in tandem with and with shared Quantum
reference frames another system and if
you now apply that kind of quantum
information Theory to the hierarchical
structures we were talking about
entailed by higher order thought Theory
and one could
imagine would be endorsed by a minimum
kind of partition under IIT then what
you have is this notion that there are
lots and lots of inner screens in our
brains which pay the role of holographic
screens from a classical point of view
mark off blankets onto which you read
and write classical information
all with a shared or common frame of
reference Quantum frame of reference
and if you have that picture in mind you
can start to ask the question well is
there a special one right deep inside
and I mean literally deep deep in terms
of the deep learning notion of a
hierarchical World model you find in
machine learning but also literally deep
in the brain where the cells of origin
that do this attentional modulation this
mental action that we were talking about
celebrated by people like Mike markson's
live and then you arrive at a notion of
a an irreducible
um set of internal neuronal States whose
Markov blanket or inner screen can never
be if you like
um can't be reduced any further and it
may be that this is a good model for
um the uh the unique aspects of
Consciousness unitary aspects of
Consciousness that are celebrated in the
IIT axioms and in a sense this is a you
know a resurrection of the Cartesian
theater it's all neocartesian ISM of a
very bold sword uh that is literally
reintroducing the notion of screens but
in a very nuanced way that actually is
very consistent with the physics of
self-organization
um because it all rests upon a free
energy principle or a Quantum version of
the free energy principle where you're
reading the holographic screens as
Markov blankets but now on the inside of
a hierarchical or I a partitionable
generative model
is that the same thing as subjective
experience
yeah
um I'm not sure that it it that you
would be the the people who are
exploring this as a sort of minimal
model that
um gracefully accommodates things like
higher order thought Theory Global
neural workspace and a number of other
Affairs would be quite so adventurous to
say at this stage yes this is what um
this explains quality of experience and
subjective experience that I think they
would argue this would be a minimal
requirement in the same spirit that I
was arguing previously that to be
um to be a self is to be an agent and to
be an agent is to act and to act is to
have a gelatin model that entails and
can generate the consequences of action
um so
um I think that most people would say
that the the sort of um
sentience of a non-basic or trivial
sword
um would certainly require this kind of
mental action that is ensues from having
um an inner screen that can never can
only see the consequences of its own
action by acting on screens that are
lower down or more superficial in the
hierarchy and that's simply because
there are no screens with inside this
minimum minimal
um uh Markov bracket or bulk
so a lot of this does rest upon action
mental action which I repeat you can
read as attention if you like it's you
know or um you know a mental action and
then if you read it along those lines
you can then
um relate it to
Notions pursued by people like Thomas
metzinger and
Limon ski where
you can render things phenomenally
transfer opaque by this kind of mental
action
um so there is I think quite a nice
story that could be built upon this
notion of an inner screen that is open
to the rest of the brain and therefore
is acting upon engaging with the rest of
the brain in a particular kind of way
that looks like mental action and
attention that enables things to become
phenomenally opaque and this would be a
prerequisite for uh for sanctions of a
certain sort so I think there's a story
to be told that I'm not sure that that
story is being put together convincingly
in the philosophical literature but you
know it may well be
um it may well be a direction of travel
over over the next few years
the next the next few years okay
um can you discuss the potential
limitations or challenges of your theory
and area where further research which is
needed so criticize your own Theory girl
right
excuse me
um well the first thing to do is to know
that the free energy principle is a
principle so it's not really there to be
criticized or falsified it's a it's a
little bit like
um Hamilton's principle of least action
you can you can apply it or or not
depending upon uh what you'd like to do
so it is in the application to various
things that that the challenges actually
arise and that's where the heavy lifting
starts
um and generally that reduces to
specifying the world model the
generative model
that is necessary to define the free
energy and that's I think where the
challenges are if you want to look at
those challenges through the lens of say
a psychologist or a neuroscientist or an
artificial intelligence researcher then
you'll be asking what are the process
theories
um that
um under this kind of generative model
would best account for the empirical
evidence that best experience how this
grade works or this artificial
intelligence works and
um you know what alternative there is
um and what are alternative message
passing schemes that would emulate the
Dynamics that would ensue when applying
the free energy principle so that that
largely is a very sort of um
inelegant summary of my my day job is
basically trying to work out your
Anatomy functional architectures
physiology in a way that I can
understand uh my brain and the brain of
my experimental subjects in terms of an
application of the free energy principle
to a generative model of a particular
sort the question is what is that
generative model and that's most of what
people are doing brain Imaging and
psychology and and neuropsychology and
electrophysiology are trying to
understand this you know how how does
the brain work my understanding this
structure
um in terms of the outstanding
challenges if you wanted to build a
brain or you wanting to build
um artificial intelligence that was more
like natural intelligence sort of
biomimetic or generalized artificial
intelligence then I think the challenges
here are first of all again identifying
the right generative model
um and it's
um uh and the um the attributes of those
generative models that speak to the
scale invariant aspects that you know
one would associate with your brain
we've talked a lot about hierarchical
gentle models but there are certain
things that are conserved As you move up
the scales
um other things are not so
um
one characteristic of these genitive
models is that as you move to a
hierarchical world models As you move to
deeper levels things slow down so you've
got a separation of Temple scales so
that would be one challenge in terms of
um incorporating more and more temporal
scales into geritive modeling or into
the generative models but you can then
apply the free energy principle to so if
you can build if you can write down
either in computed software or just in
narrative form if you can write down a
generative model everything else is
sorted you know we the 300 principle
provides you with the tools and the
methods to compute what would happen if
you let this generative model explain
its World in exactly the same way that
Hamilton's principle of least action
would allow you to compute the
trajectory of a ball if you supplied the
specification of the ball so if you can
supply the specification of the
generative model job done the problem is
getting the getting the generative model
right and that and that is not there's
not that is not easy you know
um and one could indeed say that um
this is a challenge faced not just by
life scientists in a particular
neuroscientist but it's also a challenge
um faced by Machine learning and the
artificial intelligence Community a
challenge that's made particularly more
acute when you realize that the kind of
generative models that are requisite for
surviving and modeling
um our current worlds would have to
acknowledge the fact that our worlds are
largely comprised of other things like
us so it's not just getting my
generative model right it's getting my
gelatin model of your generative model
right and getting our journey model
right and the communication between them
so taking again a sort of biometric
perspective
um what we're talking about is not just
finding the right kind of genetic models
but also understanding how they function
the implicit active inference and
learning processes
um that ensue when you put lots of these
artifacts or or systems together
and how that fits into sort of
ecosystems of shared intelligence and
shared federating inference and
Federated learning so that's that's an
outstanding challenge at the moment
um another outstanding challenge is is
being able to simulate what evolution
has done when you view Evolution as
another free energy minimizing process
and I mean that technically in the sense
that when you use free energy as a
measure of the marginal likelihood
you you are in a position then to select
certain hypotheses models or phenotypes
using Bayesian model selection and if
you look at Natural Selection as
basically Nature's way of doing Bayesian
model selection then you can read
natural selection as the use of
um Bayesian model selection based upon
variational approximations to model
evidence namely the variation for
reality G to do structure learning so by
structural learning I mean selecting the
right kinds of structures automatically
so that's still a largely
um unsolved problem in statistics and in
machine learning and it's a really
important problem so you know if you
have the right structure we now know the
maths that would be required to run that
structure in active inference for
example
um and deploy it on robots and also
generalize the notion of free energy
minimization to the parameters so you're
learning the contingencies and the the
connectivity
um but what we don't know is how to
build the right structures
so the structure learning I think is a
really important issue there
right I do want to talk about machine
learning and artificial intelligence but
if in one sec I need to get the Sun out
of my face here so give me one second
I think this is this is better all right
that's
yeah yeah so I do want to talk about
artificial intelligence you must know at
least something about it giving
computational modeling and all that
given the complexity of the brain and
the free energy principle
do you believe it's feasible to create a
truly conscious machine intelligence and
I'm putting kindness between what
because it's available whether you can
even measure it you can have a perfect
pragmatic answer or fulfill
esophageal answer or are there any
unique aspects of
biological systems
it can be replicated artificial
constructs
um
I think in principle
um provided one as soon as this notion
of
biomimetic artificial intelligence then
I've seen a reason why ultimately one
could not produce conscious artifacts of
the kind that it would not be possible
to differentiate
um we wouldn't know whether there were
conscious or not and so I I'm gonna I'm
gonna appeal to your option of giving
you a pragmatic answer
um
yeah so if if if Consciousness
is just like everything else
um a hypothesis that provides a simple
explanation for all my sense making
um then one has to ask where does it
come from on the one hand and on the
other hand acknowledge it is just a
hypothesis that explains my uh my
Sensations so I just want to pursue both
lines because they both have
implications in terms of answering your
answering your question the first line
is this notion that selfhood
um is just a hypothesis it's not
necessary to live
um yeah one can imagine viruses
um quite happily getting through being
very very successful in their life
without self-awareness and
self-consciousness so why why do we need
why do certain things act as if they
were
um self uh they had a um they had a
certain self model and awareness and one
obvious answer of course is that if our
world is populated by things like me
then I need to be able to differentiate
who the
um disambiguate the causes of certain
things when both you and I can cause
them for example speaking
um if we're having if we're really
um in a state of generalized synchrony
and we're riffing together
basically we're seeing from the same
hymn sheet and if we're singing from the
same hymn sheet I need to infer did you
say that or did I say that and
furthermore whose turn is it to talk and
whose turn is it to listen and I can
only do that if I actually have a notion
oh it's me as opposed to you and indeed
if you think about the problems faced by
a very small baby just being born into
the world
um it's going to take some time for this
baby to grow and learn a world model or
a generative model that
confirms the hypothesis that Mum is
actually separate from the baby
the mum is a thing in her own right
and it is plausible that having
established that Mum is a creature in
her own right and something that is
separate from me that I may have another
hypothesis that perhaps I am something
that's separate
from mum and the rest of the world so
you know having a notion that others
exist and then or perhaps I am like that
maybe one route to
um selfhood that inherits from really
important addict interactions that are
purely encultured but are not your
unnecessary part of this biomagnetic
kind of structure learning
um and of course that argument goes
through to all levels of communication
and uh and culturalism and community and
you know the acquisition of language and
shared narratives and so on and so forth
and all of which rest upon the notion
that I
um share a belief a world model a set of
norms a narrative frame of reference a
common ground with you
so that may be why certain things
um have selfhood and other things don't
in the sense that you know to be a virus
I don't need to talk to other other
viruses I just need to be able to
operate within my milia which is usually
inside of a host cell that I'm infecting
so that may be one one reason why
certain things
um are conscious in your in the sense of
being self-aware
um
the second theme though is that I have
generated this hypothesis and I have
confirmed it that
um but it remains just a hypothesis so
Consciousness is just like anything else
it's just a fantasy
um which means that I will never know
whether I'm conscious or and especially
I will certainly never know whether
you're conscious so the whole point of
having these uh these partitions these
Markov blankets
um that Define things is and to be able
to read the Markov blanket
um under the holographic principle is
that you can never get inside you can
only see what's on the surface so I will
never know what's going on inside your
head and I will never know whether you
are actually sense making or whether
um the or my description of your
neuronal Dynamics as basal inference and
active inference is actually true I will
just never know that all I can do is
gather evidence from your behavior and
from what you say so if that's the case
then it certainly is plausible that one
could build machines that behave
sufficiently similar to you for me to
imbue them with consciousness so
Consciousness it only lives in the head
of the person making the inference
um that you are conscious or I am
conscious it doesn't actually live in
the head of the machine so on that
pragmatic answer I would say yes there's
nothing to stop me building a machine
that would have all the characteristics
of uh Consciousness to do that I'm going
to have to be very much more by net
biomimetic also just notice that there's
a principle reason
why it would have the machine would have
to look like me and would have to have
the same epistemic affordances or
respond to the same epistemic
affordances that I do in order to be
conscious in order for me to imbue you
as Consciousness you have to be
sufficiently like me
and to be sufficiently like me
um I have to um well to infer that you
are sufficiently like me I have to be
curious about you to find out inferring
from the way you dress the way you talk
um
um Gathering evidence that you are
sufficiently like me before I can endow
you with the note with with the
attribute of being conscious like me
um that means that holds for an
intelligent art about so the intelligent
artifact will have to want to be like
you and not only that it will have to be
curious about you uh otherwise you will
never
um and it will never
um you have the capacity for
Consciousness if Consciousness is an
attribute of sense making in this sort
of Federated context so I think it's
quite important because you that means
you can't build artificial intelligence
that is conscious
unless it looks and feels almost
identical to you
but on one level there's one thing that
I had an interview Michael Levin
is a synthetic biologist I'm not sure if
you're familiar with him but he said
something that reminds me what you said
reminds me
of that and it was again I'm
paraphrasing
um that and very interesting thing
happens when you give a prompt to for
example chat gbt and we think we're we
are giving it prompts and we are asking
things but it gives us a result back but
you can also look at the result you get
back as a prompt to us
so uh good to be good good the result we
ask for actually be an inquiry because
um with these generative models they you
give you give a prompt and then you get
a certain result and then you then you
tweak it you get some extra prompts
until you get what you want but actually
what he's saying is it could be
considered as kind of a dialogue if I'm
understanding him correctly
yes you know I I know Mike very well uh
so he he was a co-author on uh that
Quantum information treatment of uh of
the theology principle
um and
um yeah that that's that's again a sort
of brilliant thought experiment I think
now you're a lot of people are putting
these large language models together so
they can talk to each other which is
exactly what we were talking about
before in terms of uh babies talking to
their mothers or me talking to you
um so I I think that is um that that
thought experiment is very prescient
um and begs the question whether these
generative AIS specifically large
language models and notice that it's not
gerited models that create
pictures or code
that pink Alaska is this is going to be
a conscious artifact or not it's just as
a generative AI systems that generate
the language
that
um invite these questions and I think
that's really important because remember
before I was trying to um paint a
picture in which Consciousness is can
only emerge in the context of uh living
in the universe comprising lots of con
specific creatures like me that um that
I can assume have the same kind of
generative model or common ground that I
do that enable communication there can
be no communication without this common
ground
and the specific thing about large
language models is that they do
communicate in language
so AI generative AI produces pictures
does not communicate in the language
and you were not confuse the journey AI
producing very realistic photographs
with a conscious artifact and you could
easily confuse a large language model
generating a conversation and actually
engaging a conversation with a large
language model you could easily start to
imbue it with Consciousness
simply because it's behaving as it was
another agent that's very much like me
using my language because that's what
it's designed to do it's great all the
data of communication in order to
reproduce as if it was having a
conversation it was communicating not in
pixels not in code not in music but in
words and I think that's what gives it
the um the potential to give the
illusion of Consciousness and I say
illusion
um
cautiously and advisably
because to actually have a generative
model under the hood would be for me a
prerequisite to actually have a you know
a true inference uh process and there
are certain arguments about whether
um you can look at large language models
um as possessing a true geritance or
World model or whether they're um
they're just detecting statistical
regularities and the sequences of words
that have been produced and can
therefore re reproduce these particular
sequences so it's a very vexed issue but
perhaps tangential to Mike Mike's point
that you know if you've got something
that can talk to you and sounds like you
even if it doesn't look and feel like
you it certainly will sound and feel
like you then it now has the um the
potential to become something that you
could infer was conscious and on that
definitely that's as that's as far as
you can ever go in my world anyway
simply because you'll never know because
you're always living on the inside of
your head
get it I get it harking back to what you
said earlier about babies
trying to realize or learn that their
mother is separate from them makes me
think about
I don't know who said that but
basically there is not really a way for
a brain to tell that the input that is
coming from me
like your brain cannot actually tell
that the input is coming from me because
the input that is coming from me to you
goes through your neurons and they don't
the neurons itself obviously do not
cannot make a distinction that that's
anyway that just popped in my mind so
but do you often work with general
knowledge yourself when you in your work
lately because this this whole large
language thing has blown up and I find
it hard to keep track of it because it's
it's going so fast it's so exciting
exhilarating I was wondering how much
you keep do you keep up with it
but I I don't keep up with the
literature or the developments as you
say in the past 100 or now especially
200 days it's it's been an absolute uh
absolutely amazing and having said that
I do work with generative models all the
time at many levels because we are all
generative models so working with my
students uh and I used to see patients
uh patients I'm working with uh
biological generative models but um yeah
seriously certainly most of my academic
um uh theoretical work is basically
um exploring and deploying generative
models usually in silico to try and
understand you know the mechanics of
um or this Bayesian mechanics and you
know the fundaments of active inference
um so yeah yeah I work all all the time
with generative models it's not quite
the same as generative AI though it's
just interesting that
um that generative AI has now come to be
known as you know things like large
language models that generate stuff when
people talk about generative models in
statistics and in theoretical biology
they mean something much closer to the
notion of a world a model in machine
learning that there's actually a
structure under the hood that's
gathering information making inferences
about States and Affairs and then
planning what to do next
um so most generative AI doesn't do that
but the kind of genital models I work
with usually purely in Academia in order
to reproduce psychological or decision
theoretic behaviors that would help us
understand how the brain works and in
particular how that those mechanisms
could fail in certain neurological and
psychiatric conditions yeah that I spend
most of my life building one kind of
gelatin model or another in Matlab like
Jeff Hinton I only use Matlab like like
Jeff Hinton does so so I'm very old
school I have I haven't learned python
or Julia yet
oh I'm I just dabbled in in programming
and it was a long time ago so I have I
have a question from let me see how fast
my laptop is
I'm not sure if you if you can see it uh
curl do you see a question on screen
girl no I'm just gonna
do you see a question
I do see a question yeah and it's saying
um you know what what would you consider
to be true General
um artificial intelligence uh yeah other
than the ability to uh convince us that
it's mastered our language and uh
ability to engage in dialogue
um I I think the answer to that
um
a game would appeal to
um this theme of biomimetic
um aspects of artificial intelligence
um and how they are deployed
um in terms of ecosystems of of it of
intelligence so
um what I've been looking for is a kind
of
um inference process and influencer
learning process that first of all is
embodied in some way
um and that has this capacity to act as
an agent so it has the capacity to
actually choose various
um to choose the data that it is going
to use as the basis of its inference and
learning
um and that's quite that's quite
important in the sense that it would
require
a move away from Big Data to Smart data
so just on the first principal account
um this notion of
um acting in a way to maximize
Information Gain means that you're
looking uh you would ascribe the notion
of generalized intelligence be it
natural or artificial to those systems
that can and that can find the smart
data actively they can data mine in the
right kind of way so I've been looking
at an intelligence
at a system for evidence that it's
mining its data smartly and implicitly
that it has a model of the consequence
of its own Mining and its own
questioning its own querying its own
palpation its own exploration
um its own epistemic foraging of the
world and if it was doing that
um in a way that was
um consistent with the free energy
principle or active inference uh that I
think you're getting quite close to
um General
um artificial intelligence or
generalized AI I would I would imagine
though that they're going to be other
qualifications on this it has to work
inside you so it has to be part of an
ecosystem as we were just talking about
in relation to Consciousness for example
there is no point in having a super
intelligence unless it's unless we are
part of that ecosystem that is a super
intelligence so it has to be
um has to be sympathetic and
self-evidizing in the context of
everything with which it is exchanging
so by definition it has to have a
certain compatibility uh and shared
epistemic goals with everything that it
is exchanging with including me
um so that would be another definite
definition of
generalized AI
thank you for asking your question Matt
MVD that's a great question
um I think he has another one
let me see
yeah on my end I don't see the question
popping up on screen so my left is
apparently lagging so much that uh you
somehow you see it soon in the night so
you can just read the question yeah
essentially
um so the question is um
what I was saying would go beyond having
access to data towards willful and free
selection of what data to access and
then there's a a question mark free will
uh and he concludes or she concludes
with I suppose therein lies are danger
so excellent yeah excellent assertion
and excellent question so that that's
absolutely right that you know this
notion of agency that underwrites the
engagement with the world the querying
the data mining or whatever situation
um or whatever perspective you want to
take on that is
um does rest upon this notion of
selecting the right policy that that's
going to get you the right kind of data
for your subsequent inference and
learning and avoiding surprises so we're
not just talking about sort of pure
epistemic exploration here this is under
constraint so the free energy is
um is not just the mutual information we
were talking about it's under
constraints so it's trying to maximize
literally the self-information in the
sense of maximizing entropy under
constraints and just for the physicists
and the audience the prediction
principle is dual to the constrained
maximum entropy principle of genes the
constraints are important these are
supplied by the generative model and it
says that some things will be surprising
um but having said that
um the the essence I think of
generalized AI or general artificial
general intelligence
um would be exactly this purposeful
selection of courses of action that
expose you to the right kind of evidence
to allow you to understand and engage
with your world
um your in an efficient and uh
synchronous synchronous fashion and you
could certainly cast the selection of
the action the epistemic policy or the
exploitative policy
as either Bayesian model selection in a
sort of mathematical sense or you could
say it is free selection in the spirit
of either quantum
mechanics or indeed philosophy there is
an active selection there when it comes
to exploring different hypotheses so I
think that's that's really important to
notice that just being an agent of the
kind that we've been talking about
entails the selection of what to do next
under our models of the consequences of
our actions that necessarily implies a
certain degree of autonomy
um and that you could describe as willed
Behavior it's certainly purposeful its
purpose is to minimize your expected to
create energy or expected surprise in
the ways that we've described but to do
that you have to select Which Way
Forward you're going to go and then the
question at the end was is that a danger
and I mean
important question
um you're strictly speaking
from my point of view
the attribute danger doesn't really get
into the game because we're talking
about self-organization of systems
um
open systems far from equilibrium and if
something
um persists in characteristic States for
a sufficient amount of time
um then it exists and can be described
as engaging in these free energy
minimizing processes so what would be
dangerous for any of these things or
when it disappeared when it died it
dissipated decayed when it no longer
maintained the Integrity of its
individuation technically the Markov
blanket that separates it from
everything else so could it be the case
that one thing causes me to dissipate
um and therefore
um causes me to go away and would be a
danger to me I mean technically it
certainly is possible and you know you
can think of speciation at an evolution
time scale
um as as we're seeing that but the you
know the whole point of the free energy
principle is um to describe systems that
actually conspire together
to maintain themselves in a in a
non-equilibrium steady state so it's
really a description of systems that are
self-sustaining
self-assembling Auto poetic in some uh
in some Elemental sense so if you've got
generalized AI
that is
minimizing
um its expected free energy
which is not optimizing a cost of
minimizing a cost function or maximizing
a value function the the only function
that matters is the
um is the evidence or the marginal
likelihood or it's expected
um bounds for conditioned upon action if
it's doing that
then that is a description of a system
that will actually self-organized to a
steady state that just is a description
of systems that are mutually sustainable
um so in that sense there can be no
danger by definition but to get to that
kind to to elude that kind of danger you
have to
commit to or assume that
um the artificial intelligence is
actually trying to minimize this it's um
minimizes its uh bound on um this uh on
surprise self-information and
information Theory or equivalently that
it genuinely is trying to self-evidence
it's trying to gather evidence for its
own existence
um and it's uh and its uh existence is
entails a model of its world and if its
World includes you then it's trying to
gather evidence about you it's trying to
understand you and therefore should
never represent a danger to you in
principle because the whole point is
that you are trying to co-construct an
ecosystem that is sustainable so this is
the fundamental distinction between
um you know optimization as growth for
example
say maximizing profit
um as opposed to optimization as a
description of
um of self-organization and
self-assemblance and self-evidencing uh
which is it certainly can be cast as an
optimization problem but the thing
you're optimizing is very specific and
it is exactly the thing that describes
self-sustaining self-assembling and
self-caring and synchronous kinds of uh
individuated artifacts
interesting there
um it sounds like you're kind of instead
of being worried about the future you
seem kind of optimistic about it
yes well I I get it quite old now so I
don't have to worry about as much future
as you have to worry about that's it
that's a very good point I like that no
but generally speaking you do not seem
too worried about this whole deal there
are a lot of people that have very
strong opinions about this I I don't see
it reflected in your words am I am I
correct in that
I think you're absolutely right I mean
part of that is the fact that I I don't
have an informed position I think that
the angst you're seeing for example
currently with um
um
generative Ai and artificial
intelligence at the moment is probably a
reflection of a greater angst about sort
of globalization and climate change and
uh your walls around around the world
um so
um you know I certainly have angst about
the you know man's inhumanity to man
I don't think that that kind of emerges
from my theoretical considerations so I
have a much more utopian view of
self-organization a much more
dispassionate
um view that you could read as
optimistic in the long in the long term
uh but I'm not denying all our dystopian
worries but I don't think they're
particularly
um if you like unique two or are owned
by
um artificial intelligence I think I
think I think you can look at any look
at that kind of angst uh of any
direction of the politician as a citizen
as a
theologian as a psychiatrist as a doctor
you'd still get the same kinds of words
yeah I don't I hear a lot of
as I said stronger beings about The
Angst or speaking you're talking about
about artificial intelligence and the
future and I do have some concerns but
not because I think it's about
Consciousness or anything like that just
but because it's not biological
and we're mimicking something we're
shaping it by our own biological drives
and needs on a system that isn't that is
by definition not biological and has no
drives so that is by far Maybe
for me personally the thing that is okay
this is dangerous because we have
absolutely in that sense no idea what
we're doing it's not wrong I'm not
saying we should stop doing it but
daring lies for me the the the danger
yeah I think it's a very Street
observation it resonates with my
repeated use of the word biometric so
you know my basic answer what is true
artificial general and generalized AI
it's that which is biometric so it's
interesting that you point out that the
moment we're actually going away we're
going the opposite direction it travels
you know billions of parameters Big Data
uh you know exactly the opposite
direction to the way that you and I make
sense of smart data so I think there's
probably going to be a U-turn in in
artificial uh intelligence research
um and you know you see this at a number
of fronts you know the concerned about
potential neuromorphic Computing for
example
um a return to uh a move from Big Data
to Smart data excitement you can get a
large language model working on your
iPhone I think that you know people
would come increasingly aware that to do
artificial intelligence properly is just
to do natural intelligence to do natural
intelligence means you have to commit to
a biometric approach
um which I think will actually you know
Larry paint will you know will pull the
direction traveled towards the kind of
um self-organizing intelligent artifacts
uh that probably will look a lot more
like Edge Computing in distributed
ecosystems that we were just talking
about
um
interesting girl
but again you see you seem optimistic I
like that I like this this approach so
um if there if there would be a truly
conscious artificial computer today
um and not the large language models
that are generated like now because it's
still there are still toys but assuming
we have fully grown artificial conscious
intelligence which I find personally
hard to believe but just hypothetically
what would she ask it and why would you
ask it
yeah
that's a great question which I don't
have a pre-prepared answer to
um but that was perfect
I was um just thinking you know if if it
is just pursuing our line of argument
that you know to be intelligent is to be
like me
um and to be like you
um the questions I would ask it are
exactly the questions that we are
exchanging at the moment you know though
you know this this is this this kind of
interview and this kind of show
I think is the Pinnacle of The Human
Condition this epistemic foraging this
um this desire to resolve uncertainty
about the kind of world that we are not
only living in but also co-constructing
and we're doing it through communication
so I would ask the same questions that
you just asked me
and probably I would be asking myself
and I do so in my everyday in my
everyday uh work simply because those
are the questions that I would ask any
intelligent person it's the intelligent
questions that you've been at you've
been asking so there's no magic there's
no it's not going to be 42 I'm afraid
that's gonna yeah and there's going to
be no secret that this super
intelligence
come ever disclose to you and me because
by definition because it is so
intelligent it is the same exactly the
same kind of intelligence that you and I
share so all that we need to know is to
what extent do we share a world view a
world model a reference frame and Common
Ground so those are the questions so the
first questions I would ask are those to
establish whether it's actually
sufficiently like me to engage in
conversation and if it is yeah because
if it's super intelligent enough then
well it either has to dumb down the
conversation just for us to understand
it or its answers will be just
indecisable for us because we're you you
mentioned super intelligence and I'm
thinking okay if there's a super
intelligence something which is
practically god let's say then then I
would have some questions of course and
I wouldn't probably wouldn't ask the
same questions I would ask Carl because
I know Carl is not it's very very very
intelligent and wise man but he's
probably not a super intelligence
yes that's a very good point and so just
to qualify what I'm about to say some
people use super intelligence as the to
refer to the kind of emergent
intelligent-like Behavior you see
um in lots of organisms that are
communicating like sort of anti-colonism
the like so it's an emergent aspect but
I think that what we're talking about
now is something that is more
intelligent than uh than me and you and
and of course
um I have to ask myself what do we mean
by intelligence
um it probably relates to the complexity
of the generative models that we've been
talking about so a world model that can
assimilate and predict
um much more of the universe than we can
that has a broader view of things so as
you say something that has a more of a
God's eye view or as a godhead
um that can see the Dark Side of the
Moon and knows what it's like to be in
the middle of the of the Sun or knows
what it's like life is like on other
planets so this would just be a very big
geratin model that had more access to
more kinds of data
and the question is though if it had a
sufficiently different genitive model
that did not include our little world
and the problem is it would not be able
to talk to us because there wouldn't be
any shared frames of reference so there
would be no question and answers you'd
only I think be able to talk to this
kind of god-like super intelligence If
part of its generative model included
our lived world and those beliefs that
pertain to our live world could be
deployed in order to describe other
worlds that we that we do not have
direct access to so yeah there'll be a
lot of strong requirements on this super
intelligence that again speak to its um
consilience and sympathy and
synchronization with us again saying
that your intelligence in and of itself
is not an attribute that is not
relational you know something is only
intelligent in relation to the thing
that it is exchanging with so the
intelligence is a relational notion just
in the same way there I think
Consciousness probably is a relational
notion
um it's just that self-consciousness is
relating to myself or in a screens
Within Myself
um and I think probably intelligence is
the same so you know I'm just thinking
about yeah you're absolutely right so if
I could speak to
um somebody who has been who is more
cultured than I am somebody who had
lived in you know every continent there
was or indeed in Mars and I've seen
every culture somebody uh you know had a
generative model that was able to
explain more than my more limited
gelatin model code
um then I would ask a question about
where have you been what do you see what
was it what was it like absolutely
that's what I think
it's fine we we we're getting there at
the end so perfect thank you I like this
answer I have some I have a question
from someone else again my laptop is
slow so if you see before I do you can
just read what it's what it says oh wait
I can see it
um DS Atkinson he asks um I'm late
coming in but would you mind asking him
his thoughts on Donald Hoffman and his
theories of Consciousness we have not
covered Donald Hoffman here yet
um I'm not sure um
how much Carl knows about this girl
I I yes I I was once called by Jerry
Adelman an intellectual Thug which means
I
know a lot but I don't know everything
forgive me I have no philosophical
training so could you just summarize for
me and and everybody else the main
tenets of Donald Hoffman's position I I
have heard of him and I I've been asked
this question before but just to make
sure I've got the right well I'm not
going to do him justice so I'm gonna
make it make it small he's a scientist
who has a theory about reality and that
reality is subjective is it's not an
objective reality it's something we
project and he has done simulations on a
computer proving that if you make
species compete and one species has a as
I said objective view of reality and the
other one has just what it needs to
survive then the one that that has the
theory that just is enough to survive
even if it's wrong it's actually
especially when it's wrong this is the
one that will always outperform the
other so his his idea is that or is his
notion is that in reality as we see it
is most certainly wrong and he can his
claims that he can mathematically prove
that and he's made a mathematical Theory
and it is mathematically a pluralist
theory in a sense that he need at least
two conscious agents to begin with
but philosophically speaking he admits
that he is a monist and that's as an
idealist that Consciousness is the
source of existence and everything
particles and and energy and all that
kind of stuff is a projection from
conscious agents like agreements between
them not sorry I'm butchering your
theory but this is as far as I can
briefly explain it
well that was really useful
um and everything you said made perfect
sense to me and I sort of
rap Bell so somebody's clearly jealous
and try to explain it briefly uh in
previous conversation but um everything
that I think sounds perfectly consistent
you know this notion of
um having uh wrong models that are
optimal in the sense of being sufficient
to um explain and predict our exchanges
with the lived world is is to my mind
absolutely right it sounds very much
like the notion of satisficing there's a
whole
um theorizing uh um
um where Simplicity or minimum
minimization complexity is the objective
function and this inherits directly from
um the um the sort of information
theoretic perspective that you get from
the free energy principle in all its
carnations
um uh and certainly would be the line um
that somebody like Jurgen schmidtiver
would pursue them to compress is to have
the best kind of model and that that
compression can be scored by the
variational free energy and you will
find it in economics and you know in the
sense of heuristics and satisficing
um of the kind promoted by gerd garenza
um and you will find it in the in
machine learning and data science in the
form of compression
um so again you know only having that
stuff that you need everything else
being redundant so your models have to
be as simple as possible as a
statistician I think this was a really
fundamental point because you know if
you just write down the expression for
model evidence the marginal likelihood
of your data given a particular model
and you write down or decompose the log
logarithm of the evidence you can always
express it as accuracy minus complexity
that means to do good self-evidencing to
have high adaptive Fitness for example
just means to write an accurate account
of your sensorium as simply as possible
by minimizing the complexity so it
doesn't surprise me in the site is that
when you simulate agents who have the
simple the right kind of simple model as
Einstein said you know keep everything
as simple as possible but no simpler so
there's a Goldilocks theme of Simplicity
I'm dumbing down and that will always
outperform somebody who is
um overfitting their world and having
very very accurate true models are
certainly closer to the gerited process
um
and you find that you know basic
phenomena emerging everywhere not just
in data compression but in overfitting
for example
um in machine learning where they run to
things like sort of sharp Minima uh
simply because they're overfitting the
data they need to simplify things by
mini batching or blurring data for
example so as a deep truism there which
means that all your models are wrong so
it's absolutely right but they're the
best models that's that's the important
thing if they've maximized the uh the
evidence
um the the the you talked about the
relational aspect and monism
um and that um
physics is a construction I think most
physicists would agree with that you
know um you know physics is measurement
to measurement is inference and most of
uh certainly sort of relational quantum
mechanics would would certainly say that
you know
um most of the things that we actually
deal with are uh can only be described
in terms of observation and measurement
I've just read um uh Carla raveli's uh
book Helga land which is beautiful that
convinced me even more that everything
is is as you as you put it relational or
uh uh certainly arising from triadic or
dyadic interactions and measurement
yeah I find that the theories that deal
with information as a fundamental
a fundamental thing of nature or even
the most fundamental thing I find them
always hard to grasp and it's silly
because on the other hand I have no
problem uh considering that
Consciousness is fundamental and it all
exists is consciousness and interactions
within Consciousness and that all
particles and and stuff like that are
manifestations implementation I have no
problem with that but when someone says
you know reality is just information
somehow it just doesn't click I see
numbers and I'm like okay how can
reality be pure information yeah but I
mean that that's the message message
throughout this and I mean you know
Richard Feynman your energy is
information uh you're it from this you
know wherever you look
um
well certainly as I get older and I did
physics
um quantum physics and probability
Theory as a young man and I thought that
was reality I thought Quantum you know
that's the description of reality but as
I get older I I start to realize that
even
classical quantum physics or classical
mechanics Cisco mechanics quantum
mechanics and even I think the Bayesian
mechanics of the free energy principle
these are all just stories they're just
stories that are part of my generative
model that I've some some of my teachers
have shared with me
um that that
you'll have as much uh if you like
um veracity as my fantasies I am me or
that you know or anything else that
characterizes my beliefs and
explanations for the work for the um for
the of of of my world
um so
I know what you mean uh but I'm pretty
sure it's right that your notion of an
atom and a particle have you ever seen
an atom
no no I used to think no I used to well
they they made beautiful pictures and
drawings and animations but apparently
you kind of make a photograph because
they're smaller than the waist length of
light so light passes over it at least
that's a metaphor they gave me so I'm at
the states that okay this is just useful
metaphors nothing wrong with them but
they are metaphorical just like almost
anything we describe in reality but
that's just makes it easier for me to
think about these things they're useful
models well absolutely I mean making it
easy to think about them is exactly the
sort of you know the free energy
minimizing process that we were talking
about having those good fluid simple
models that make the most sense of
everything that we encounter but just
think about what you said you find it
very difficult to think about a universe
that is composed just of information and
numbers but much easier to think of it
comparison atoms and yet you've never
actually seen an atom and even if you
could you would be able to see it
even worse fantasies at least you can
see a number
so you know isn't it straight the way
our brains compell us to try and find
these very simple
um your intuitive uh good enough
sufficient stories to explain our world
even physics
and physics changes every year you know
there's no ground truth there it's you
know it's uh
no I I have well I I used to think that
there was an objective truth and then I
didn't think there was an objective
series and now I'm just I I don't know
it's just I'm I'm getting pretty
agnostic the older I get so
um but you're right the stories we tell
ourselves is uh is one of the most
interesting things it's also the way how
our language works it is metaphorical
everything almost everything is a story
a theory is a story from beginning to
end that's just how it seems to work
there are certain archetypes how these
stories are are built and this is how we
understand it and it's just it blows
around why this is apparently the only
way that it works for us or maybe
that is what language is I don't know
I'm just
so
um someone else oh wait DSX had one
other question it will be cool to ask
him about his opinion about UFOs well
that's totally different direction but
why not this isn't you can ask any
question here so Carl
um there we go one question to another
question no relationship but what do you
think of UFOs or uaps as they are
cult nowadays
um
I guess the the question is
um well I mean certainly if you know if
you if there are what is on the tin then
they're just unidentified and surprising
and unexplainable so they will certainly
attract our attention
um under the French principle or if
we're doing the right kind of um active
inference if the implicit question is
you know
is there other kind of intelligent life
form elsewhere I think that you know
that that is an interesting question
which again I am not I don't have an
informed view on and my my sort of back
of an envelope
um calculations just looking at the
probability that
um we have co-evolved to a similar level
of intelligence with allow you know you
mention it communication so the only way
that would actually you know see a UFO
is one way of communicating it's it's a
deontic cue it's a sign that there's
something roughly at our side eyes and
you know it has the same kinds of
physics of us that is around that can uh
to be in the same spatial location under
my uh physics and stories of my world
um the probability of that happening I
think is fantastically small so I'd be I
would be extremely surprised if there
were if there was a lot if there were
aliens
um driving unit and identified flying
objects around the earth very very
surprised simply because there are so
many constraints that would render
um render the probability of that
happening under my physics World model
my my intuitive physics
um
yeah there seem to be a lot of reasons
why uh aliens well the time it takes to
travel the fact that you can go faster
than light
um the
if it takes like I don't know 10 000
years to get here then by the time they
get here maybe their civilization has
died out and they forgot even forgot why
they got here in the first place and
maybe alien life is so different than us
that simply are not able to see it and
then they are not able to see us in the
list goes on so there's there are enough
reasons I I kind of agree there it seems
like a slim chance the fact that they
might exist sure but why not it seems
awfully possible that they exist but so
it actually answered this DS Atkinson I
have another question
um let me see if that that's the right
one mad MPD asked makes me really wonder
what happens to the energy within us
upon death to where does it dissipate
what form must it take and the age-old
question where does Consciousness go
after we die
right so again sorry we're just picking
your brain on all kinds of things one
want to know how your brain works how
things think about things so
right so
um so from a point of view of the sort
of physics of self-organization I mean
death is um you know a really
interesting
um phenomena in the sense it is exactly
a failure of this maintenance of this
individuation of the thing from
everything else
um and you know certainly using the word
dissipators I think very very
interesting you could have used a word
Decay or dissolve all of these words
basically reflect that there is a loss
of the Integrity of the Markov blanket
or the separation of you as a living
thing from the rest of your world so
um you know I'm just picking up on the
use of the word dissipate here
um
it is I think possibly
um inevitable of all self-organizing
processes because this this kind of
um process of self-assembly
um
and sustainability into an attracting
set cannot uh has to be if you like
um reproduced over increasing time
scales which means that there is always
a time scale where things die very very
quickly from your point of view and
there's always a time scale above where
things last for an eternity from your
point of view so for example
um for me as a body
um a lot of my cells actually die very
very frequently and indeed when I ever I
cut my hair
um I'm discarding some part of my body
that has died and that will dissipate
um that would be looking at a you know
at things at a smaller faster time scale
that indeed could actually constitute me
at my time scale but also there's a time
scale at say evolutionary time scale or
cosmological time scale that is much
longer so if I am me and my con
specifics I could endure for or
thousands of if not millions of
generations but each at each level there
will be an Inception and a dissipation
um that is just part of this nested
um uh kind of self-organization that can
be described as self as if you like
self-evidencing or free energy
minimization just in virtue of this
um
existence of solutions to certain states
of being that is expressed again and
again in this nested way over over
different time scales and where does the
energy go
um that speaks the notion of
conservation of energy but what I've
just described is something that is not
conserved when it dies and so I prefer
to think of this as
um from interpreting energy really and
purely in terms of information and the
processes the information processing
that is entailed by sense making and by
living and so in many respects
um
you don't have to worry about
thermodynamic energy
it is the energetic processes read as
making senseless perception and active
sensing that as the expression of the uh
if you like the informational aspects of
um of of of the energy and just being
and possibly even being conscious is
probably
um best thought of as a process that
could be read as consuming energy and
when that energy is no longer consumed
that is when you die
um but of course in your death death
there will also be other things will be
reborn from your death
um either at an evolutionary time scale
or indeed in terms of
um your what's happens to your to your
atoms I'm sort of wandering away from
the question now because I I'm not sure
what kind of energy that we would we
were talking about and I would read
energy really as
um I repeat
a potential
literally as like a voltage
um where that potential is always red as
a log probability which brings us right
back to the notion of information which
means that you're in a very simple sense
energy and information are the same
thing but things are processes and that
means it's the way that we handle energy
and handle information which defines us
and in a sense death is the cessation of
that kind of processing
thank you all right another one which is
people are asking questions finally guys
this is what I this is why I'm using
stream yard so you guys can ask
questions
um so a question from
I'm not sure how to pronounce it
seriously cheat I think you talk about
choosing free energy to explore future
consequences but what about reflecting
on past actions I see self-reflectivity
as a key characteristic of general
intelligence personally yep I I I'd
agree entirely
um so
that notion of um introspection and
um
self-reflection and indeed reflecting on
past actions
um is speaks very much to what I was
what we were talking about previously in
terms of the the essential role of
memory
um and uh and planning and memory in
planning and one aspect of
um that planning is that one can improve
one's World models one's internal models
or generative models by effectively
rehearsing what has happened to you and
maximizing the efficiency of those
models but interestingly usually
involves a not an increase in the
accuracy because whilst you're
reflecting or introspecting there's no
more data that you're trying to
assimilate so that you there is no
notion that you're trying to maintain
the accuracy of your expressions of data
because there are no data however if you
remember we were just saying before the
log evidence which the free energy
approximates or bounds is equal to
accuracy minus complexity this means you
can still self-evidence by minimizing
the complexity of your morals and
um
one way of doing that is basically to
resolve do house cleaning if you like
and remove redundant aspects of Your
World models during periods of
interception and some people also argue
um during sleep as well during dreaming
for example that these are excellent
opportunities to continue self-evidising
in your head by looking for associations
by resolving uh or eliminating redundant
parameters of your generative model that
would otherwise rendered them too
complicated and with a tendency to
overfit so one picture of this is uh
Julia it's an owner's picture for
example of uh synaptic homeostasis that
we spend our entire working day ratting
through life building up all sorts of
associations in terms of brain
connections or synaptic Connections in
the brain
um and then we have quiet Amendments of
interception of introspection uh
possibly
um
mindfulness and certainly sleep during
which we can
revisit all those associations and
remove all the unnecessary and
incidental associations in terms of
synaptic Connections in the brain so
that we wake up the following morning or
in a refreshed way with a slightly
simple explanation uh that has stood the
test of time as it were so I think
that's absolutely crucial and you see
that empirically in those sorts of
contextual
um even little mice running around mazes
will
emit
um signals from their brains suggesting
that they're actually replaying and
rehearsing what they're going to do and
what they have just done in order to
consolidate and to install the right
simple kinds of gelatin models in the
head that are apt for navigating this
particular situation
thank you thank you girl
um what are your thoughts on ndes
near-death experiences
I said nothing to do with your field
still curious
their death experiences
exactly right I've never had one but it
it I had a friend who really wanted to
ask you that question right
I mean these um often associated with
Altered States Of Consciousness
um and they um
I think that they're terribly
um informative and presumably if you've
ever experienced them
um can be quite life-changing and indeed
one might imagine that the the
experience of these Altered States Of
Consciousness are sometimes the
aspirational goal of certain
um meditative practices or mindfulness
practices and indeed some uh therapeutic
applications that engage the
um the sense making systems that we were
talking about before in relation to
mental action and attention so from my
perspective
um the um you know a typical near-death
experience and out-of-body experience
for example the might be characterized
by seeing yourself you leave your body
or you might
um see
um
a
um a particular sort of photic stimulus
a bright light for example
um so these are sort of characteristic
experiences that are reported by people
who have
um had near-death um experiences and
they all speak to I think um you know a
very important aspect of our sense
making first of all they do reveal how
fragile our fantasies and our hypotheses
are so if you take psychedelic drugs for
example that act upon exactly the same
mechanisms that may be
um engaged during their death
expenses either physiologically or
non-physiologically depending on the
kind of trauma that was inside of an
in-depth experience
um that you you will you will experience
how fragile our sense making can be in
terms of simple Notions like uh time is
Flowing or um you know sounds are
actually seen as opposed to heard
um or that um you know my body is all
joined up and doesn't fly around for
example or that I live inside my body uh
usually just behind the eyes all of
these are as fantastic Notions uh as
Jackson notion of an atom which is never
actually seen
so quickly dissolved
um I am me I'm a person you know these
are very very fragile hypotheses that
can easily be
um if you like uh removed either in
certain psycho um psychopathological
conditions or psychiatric conditions or
by taking drugs or by
um trauma
um that is um experienced uh you know
unfortunately by some people normally
what they involve with uh is
um involved is um this um
aberrant selection
of evidence for sense making at various
levels in these hierarchical models and
biologically what that looks like is a a
failure of or
um an aberrant function of something
called neuromodulation now
neuromodulation just means modulating
the excitability of neurons brain cells
that communicate messages that cause
this belief updating and sense making uh
passing messages from one level of the
hierarchy to the next level of the
hierarchy and it's very important which
messages you pass
both upwards in terms of the prediction
errors and downwards to provide context
and constraints in the form of
predictions for sense making at the
level below and one way in which you
select these it is thought is to
um
it enables certain
um uh ascending messages that are sent
deep into the hierarchy through these
gain mechanisms either read as
intentional gain or postsynaptic gain if
you're an electrophysiologist that are
mediated by certain neurotransmitters
and interestingly it's the transmitters
that are affected the transmitters that
are affected by psychedelics and by
psychotropics and most drugs using
neurology and Psychiatry
these drugs act exactly upon these
neuromodulatory mechanisms so
um I would imagine that most near-death
experiences fall into this class of
Altered States of sense making where
there are no constraints on or you are
dissolving certain deep constraints by
removing through a bare neuromodulation
um
moving the constraints on certain kinds
of sense making at particular levels in
a hierarchical model which enable you
now to experience the world in a very
very different way I do repeat though
that this is sometimes a therapeutic
objective
um you know imagine that you
um for example were very depressed
and had built a model of your world in
which you know anything you did was we
met by rejection or hostility or
potential uh you know egoistonic
responses and the best thing is just to
stay in bed and and do nothing and the
problem with these kinds of world models
is that they preclude you going and
searching evidence that challenges that
model and that hypothesis so the very
factual disengaging socially
in terms of interpersonal genetic
interactions means you can never test
the hypothesis that everyone is going to
be nasty to me
which means that there's no challenge so
these if you like self-assembling
malignant hypotheses sometimes you want
to actually Challenge and resolve and
one way of doing that is to
um
Target these neuromodulatory mechanisms
either by using drugs or by
um engaging in certain attentional
practices so you you become skilled at
actually activating and deactivating
these modulation systems to allow
yourself to explore other ways of being
other hypotheses about your interaction
with the world
um and I'm thinking here about
meditation practices internal attention
States mindfulness practices some with
or without the use of psychedelics to to
augment that and they can be very
powerful these uh these modulatory
modulatory drugs I don't know if that
helps I haven't had a near-death
experience so I can't speak no no no it
wasn't my it was a question from for
someone else so I can speak for them but
I hope it was it was helpful to them uh
you said something that interests me
though that there are some things that
you find much more interesting or at
least as much as interesting like uh I'm
in my body and
um
there are a couple there were a couple
you mentioned anyway one I I like to I
love to read one book by Oliver's sex I
think he's called
s-a-c-k-s and he had some stories about
patients and I think one of those
stories was uh about someone who was
dislocated from their body like a couple
of centimeters to the back and then a
couple of centimeters up so they were
always looking
looking somewhat down on their body and
and when so when they had to you know
when they had to grab something they
they always missed so they had to
purposefully
relocate their hand in a very awkward
way to magically somehow grab the cup
they want want to want to get and there
was always also a case by of a patient
who had who was stuck on the ceiling and
was looking back upon themselves and
while they tested it obviously by
writing someone something on a paper and
putting in putting it with the letters
upwards towards the ceiling and ask ask
the patient if you could read it and
obviously he couldn't or he made
something up but it was very convincing
that that's the first thing I think
about when um when I think about
near-death experience or no no Out of
Body Experience yeah but I would like to
maybe there will be a pill or a drug or
something that I could try that for like
20 minutes that would be so cool just
for 20 minutes just be just be on the
ceiling how that feels or not be in my
body it will be I think it would be very
interesting experience so
you should you should invite um Mark
soles
um to talk to you I don't know if you've
cut
it
how do you spell his last name so
s-o-l-m-s mark his his world expert on
um what's called neuropsychoanalysis
um which is basically a mixture of
neuropsychology brain lesion experiments
and clinical treatment
um in neurology and psychoanalysis and
is also one of the world's experts on uh
Freud and Neo Freudian thinking
um but he he you know he has some really
great ideas about Consciousness but also
has lots of patients of the kind uh that
you've just described for example so
fascinating yeah it really is you should
you should get a monetary you know one
of his um Amy Dorman is one of his
colleagues and she has a a patient or
not as a patient just you know somebody
um that um she uh she investigates whose
visual system is just reversed so she
sees everything wow when you see her
from left to right right
she
sees it as going from right to left and
she has to compensate and only realize
this when she went to University and
started actually talking about the
direction in which things moved or so
and really fascinating how how easily
our geometric our perspective taking
models can go wrong with certain kinds
of you know aberrant
neurophysiology or Anatomy
um and in light of that if you also
there's a Temple called David rudroff
Rudd Ross are you
um our auf
um who's currently
um he's been Grenoble is currently
relocated to France and he's a great
theoretician who has a whole projective
um geometry Theory Of Consciousness that
really does put where you think you are
center stage in building models of how
we engage and act in our world and of
course you know where we are physically
and how we move our bodies around is a
really important part of that yeah
because you're not you're not in your
foot right now you're somewhere here
which is kind of super strange if you
think about I wonder if that's also one
of these things that is just efficient
maybe or maybe there's some reality
principle going on there but I I wonder
I actually they wonder about that
somewhat earlier it's like why am I not
in my foot why my hand
yeah yes it seems we all share this
apparently with about two centimeters
just behind the midline of our eyebrows
apparently that's where most of us put
ourselves but it's a really interesting
why why why would that be the vantage
point and David's theory of projective
geometry as a key architectural
principle of the charity of the world
models we have given our kind of bodies
that we have to use whether our eyes are
have evolved or are engineered
um you know that provides some really
interesting insights into your the
Vantage points and where where am I
but thank you for the recommendation
I'll I'll look him up thank you has he
really has he written any books Mark
sons and Bob Services written a number
of books I think the most recent one was
called The Hidden Spring by Mark Sims
um but he you know he's quite a prolific
and and a very well-known International
speaker
um so you should be able to find so
Linson came to town that travels the
world
um yeah seeing um academics and and uh
patients and the like and the other
gentleman was David rudroff who was
younger and hasn't uh written a book yet
to my knowledge but he has certainly
written some very interesting high-end
papers in in this in this field where
there's nothing yeah I'm a good reading
papers but luckily we live in the age of
30 GPT so I can ask for a summary right
um so girl were there any moments in
your personal or experience in your
personal life that you say have
significantly shaped or redirected your
research in theoretical neuroscience and
computational modeling
um I I think most of the decision points
were uh formative and absolutely crucial
yeah um so I I don't think there was you
know there were no specific events
because very much as we were talking
about before in terms of having a
narrative
um having a willful narrative about
what's going to happen to me next and
actively putting yourself in that
position that's been very much where
I've designed my career so every move I
have made has been chosen in order to
um align with this access or direction
of
um responding to epistemic affordances
to put myself into a situation where I
could ask questions and try to answer
them
um doing your theoretical neuroscience
so formative ones were were
um I haven't got time to tell the story
but ending up doing uh Psychiatry for
example that was very important and uh
spending two years in a
um an old Victorian style Lunatic Asylum
with 20 to 30 chronic schizophrenics and
psychiatric nurses and colleagues uh in
in a community setting now for two years
that was quite interesting
formative type of I can imagine
I can yeah there must be a lot of good
stories there maybe maybe for another
time but yeah it's very interesting so
um
and the other way around the dot has
your work how has your understanding of
it
influence your daily decisions and how
you think about the world as is it going
the other way around
yes I think that's certainly true
um I mean a lot of the common sensical
um interpretations of active inference
um are those that actually comply with
the free energy principle they are
accurate but really simple explanations
for observed behavior and of course you
know I observe my behavior more than
anybody else is so a lot of it a lot of
this is yes that makes a lot that's a
simple explanation what for why I did
this or why I deceived that or why I
thought that or why I planned that
um so yeah so there is a circular
causality
what's that moment where like well if I
hadn't done this work then I wouldn't be
this person or
escrow always been this person and he
always knew what to do and uh
this work didn't change his inner
perspective on life
oh
um
it is too personal it's you don't have
to share it I'm just curious
I'm just trying to think about your
entertaining but uh sensible answer
no I think I think I just feel I was
very lucky
um I you know um
I don't think I've actually used any
theoretical insights to further my
career
um having said that perhaps there is one
interesting example which is um
I came into science
um in the context of brain Imaging and
uh first contributed by writing uh
software packages for analyzing brain
Imaging data specifically statistical
parametric mapping with colleagues
um and subsequently procedures that we
mentioned right at the beginning of the
interview such as Dynamic causal
modeling
having to solve the problem of how to
analyze scientific data
exposed me
um in part to the principles of more
generic modeling and sense making
um which meant that
um it was easy for me to see how one can
apply exactly the same principles that
we were using to analyze our scientific
data to the brain when it was trying to
analyze its sensory data and very
fortuitously at that time people like
Jeffrey Hinton and Peter Diane had just
moved next door to our brain Imaging
unit and we're telling a very similar
story from the point of view of the
importance of gelatin models in making
sense of data in the context of
artificial intelligence and machine
learning as it was
um in the in the early 90s so I think
the Confluence of those two things were
very formative in terms of you know
translating basic statistical and
mathematical principles and methods into
a story about biological
self-organization and in particular you
know sort of Neuroscience that then can
be generalized to any kind of biotic
self-organization
we're nearing the two and a half hour
mark so I don't want to take up too much
of your time I'm I'm not sure how how
much energy you have I don't want to be
rude we haven't discussed this because
we just went and went into an interview
but usually around 90 minutes two hours
I'm like okay how are you doing should
we go on do you want to eat something I
have a break or just end it
um so here's that moment do you want to
go on or like no Jack it's uh I'm done
for today I have to see my wife whatever
have my kids
um let's do one more question or uh if
you have one and then sure I've tons of
questions yeah okay well then it's um
well silly question actually um if you
well Carl if you could have a
conversation with any historical figures
whether scientists philosopher religious
leader whatever about our views who
would it be and what would it be about
um I'll be torn between helmholtz and
Richard Feynman I think
um ooh Simon yeah yeah
there are lots of great thinkers but
certainly for me for me or my heroes
apart from Sherlock Holmes is not a real
person is is
our helmholtz the other polymath and
Richard Feynman so it would be nice I
don't know that I'd have anything
sensible to ask them but at least I
could say I'd spoken to them and be very
proud of that well I have been a fan of
when I was younger I I listened to the
the audio books the the fireman lectures
on physics and oh oh boy there was one
this man could explain anything to you
it was it was so gorgeous to listen to
his stories the way
the way he explained it it made he made
everything simple and he had such a joy
such a wonderful way of teaching
teaching me things and it was really
genuine and it wasn't even teaching he
was just telling stories but what what
what if you what would you have asked
either of them because you would have
you would like to speak with them if you
could but I'm curious what would you
have asked them right well I I I I I
would have
um I'd like to have known where their
contributions came from that you know in
exactly the same way you the the past
two questions have been asking me about
you yeah where how did my life story and
career
um intersect with and cause the um the
academic contributions I would also have
the same kind of Fascination for these
people's epistemic journals at what
point did they have these insights and
what point were they articulated what
was the colonel Freud and do we
understand them now in the spirit in
which they were originally invented
would I be particularly interested in
because
what would have happened if helmheltz
had met Feynman see help help
um I think had all the right ideas that
you know that one could even argue under
right generative AI you know and the
past hundred days of great achievements
in uh in um in machine learning and
artificial intelligence research he had
all the right ideas right from the
physics right from sort of helmhole
speak compositions and help holds free
energy right through to the uh the
psychology and the um his work on
perception and Optics and like you know
he knew I think he knew an enormous
amount and
um
tried to find a unifying principle for
all of this intelligence and this uh he
framed it unconscious inference
um in terms of a neuronal energy or a
neural energy they'll play the same role
as a Helen Health Energy or a Gibbs
energy in um free energy in a um in
thermodynamics
um and really failed
um and it's interesting that Freud at
the time was coming up with his Notions
shortly afterwards of you know an
energetic and bound energies and the
like and I'm I I would like to ask him
to one extent Freud was was trying to
take this
um this narrative further and but just
didn't have the right sort of um uh the
right physics grounding but specifically
what would have happened if
um if helmheltz had met Feynman because
Feynman I think came up with the right
kind of free energy that helmhurstle's
looking for in his in his uh work on the
pathological formulation and Quantum
electrodynamics that's the free energy
that is the free energy of the free
energy principle it's this thing that is
is used to do good modeling to work out
the probability of things which normally
you wouldn't be able to do because you
didn't you you you couldn't solve this
impossible marginalization or
intractable marginalization problem but
he worked out a way of doing it of the
kind that could be used by biophysical
systems like the brain and had firemen
been able to talk to helmholtz I'm sure
that we would have got things like the
free energy principle not in the early
21st century but in the in the early
20th century
the two of them to talk to each other I
think yeah you'll you'll be out of a job
then so it maybe it's for the best girl
right
girl thank you for your time really
um I appreciate it so much people here
here too
um
enjoy your day and I'm not sure how the
weather is it looks very nice behind you
it looks very sunny it's super sunny
here so I'm gonna enjoy the last less
bits of sunshine too and uh
yeah just thank you for this for this
conversation I really enjoyed it yes
well I did as well thank you very much
for having me I can see I can see the
sunshine fading behind you so now I have
very much enjoyed the questions uh and
didn't realize that so much time had
passed you're absolutely right so thank
you
thank you and uh I hope we speak again
if not girl
um Good Luck
cheers